{"tossups": [{"question": "Works in this medium include Kelly Turnbull's Manly Guys Doing Manly Things. Other Canadian artists working in this medium include Kate Beaton and Ryan North, who produce Hark a Vagrant and a work featuring Utahraptor and T-Rex that is updated at (*) qwantz.com [dot com]. Saturday Morning Breakfast Cereal is in, for ten points, what online medium used for xkcd [x-k-c-d] and The Oatmeal?", "answer": "webcomics (prompt on comics)", "subcategory": "Trash Other", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "This civilization's spiritual rituals were recorded in the Chilam Balam manuscripts and were based on a 260-day cycle that was extended by the Long Count system. A demon named Seven Macaw is defeated by Hunahpu and Xbalanque, the Hero Twins, as told by this culture's (*) Popul Vuh. For ten points, name this Mesoamerican culture whose calendar did not actually predict a 2012 apocalypse and which built the Temple of Kukulcan at Chichen Itza.", "answer": "Mayan civilization (culture, etc.)", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "As US President, this man authorized the voyage of the Great White Fleet and brokered the Treaty of Portsmouth, ending the Russo-Japanese War. (*) \"Speak softly and carry a big stick\" was a personal motto of this Bull Moose Party founder, who succeeded William McKinley. For ten points, name this president who is depicted on Mount Rushmore with Washington, Jefferson, and Lincoln.", "answer": "Theodore \"Teddy\" Roosevelt (prompt on \"Roosevelt\" alone)", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A sculpture by this artist includes six figures walking solemnly while wearing nooses, The Burghers of Calais. This sculptor never completed his Gates of Hell, which includes a sculpture of Paolo and Francesca da Rimini (*) embracing and one of a man pensively resting his chin on his fist. For ten points, name this French sculptor of The Kiss and The Thinker.", "answer": "Auguste Rodin", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Rocket scientists calculate the force needed for this quantity to rise high enough to escape a planet's gravitational pull. Objects in free fall accelerate until they reach the terminal type of this quantity. This quantity can change with either a change in direction or with (*) acceleration or deceleration, because it is a vector quantity, not a scalar. For ten points, name this physical quantity that describes speed in a direction.", "answer": "velocity (accept escape velocity or terminal velocity; prompt on speed before \"direction\" is read)", "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This author created a lawyer's assistant who answers, \"I would prefer not to\" in response to every request in the story \"Bartleby the Scrivener.\" In a novel by this man, a gold coin is nailed to the (*) Pequod's mast as an incentive for sailors like Queequeg and Ishmael. For ten points, name this author of a novel about Ahab's search for a white whale, Moby Dick.", "answer": "Herman Melville", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This integer is the square root of the largest perfect square in the Fibonacci sequence. A polyhedron with six vertices and eight faces will have this many edges. This value, represented in hexadecimal as \"C,\" is the number of edges on a (*) cube and the number of faces on a dodecahedron. For ten points, name this smallest integer divisible by both 4 and 6, the number of items in a dozen.", "answer": "twelve", "subcategory": "Science Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "One of this country's monarchs, John the Good, negotiated the Treaty of Bretigny [breh-ti-nee] after being captured at Poitiers [pwa-ti-yay]. This country lost a battle on St. Crispin's Day to an army led by Henry V. Forces from this country rallied around the (*) \"Maid of Orleans,\" who was burned at the stake. For ten points, name this country that was defended by Joan of Arc during its Hundred Years' War with England.", "answer": "Kingdom of France", "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The guqin \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc is a Chinese member of this instrument family, which also includes the bouzouki and an instrument sometimes played with hammers, the dulcimer. Zithers and (*) sitars are also members of this family, which are played by plucking or strumming. For ten points, name this family of instruments that includes guitars and violins.", "answer": "string instruments (accept chordophones; accept word forms; accept zither before mentioned)", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In a story by this author, \"The Lass of Aughrim\" is sung while Gretta Conroy reminisces about Michael Furey. In a novel by this man, Blazes Boylan has an affair with Molly, the wife of Leopold Bloom, who represents the title hero of this man's stream-of-consciousness novel (*) Ulysses. For ten points, \"The Dead\" is a short story from Dubliners, a collection by what Irish author?", "answer": "James Augustine Aloysius Joyce", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "According to a 1946 work, members of this ethnic group were not interested in letting their families know they were safe in prison. This ethnic group's \"shame culture\" is contrasted with American \"guilt culture\" in Ruth Benedict's The (*) Chrysanthemum and the Sword. For ten points, name this ethnic group that was persecuted in the US during World War II after the Pearl Harbor attacks?", "answer": "Japanese-Americans", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Jared Diamond explained how this process, as part of a general exploitation of resources, doomed the Rapa Nui on Easter Island. The Sumatran oranguatan has become endangered due to this process, which is common in Indonesia as (*) palm oil consumption has increased. For ten points, name this ecologically-dangerous process in which a tree-heavy biome is cleared and converted to human use, a process that is currently endangering the Amazon.", "answer": "deforestation (accept word forms and equivalents that describe any type of forest being cleared or otherwise artificially destroyed; prompt on clearing before \"cleared\" is read; do not accept or prompt on natural processes like wildfires that may have the same effect)", "subcategory": "Science Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In 2005, this country's leader promised free heating oil for poor Americans; that support was provided through Citgo, the American arm of this country's national oil company. This country's current president is Nicolas Ma \u0301duro, who succeeded a man who controlled (*) South America's largest oil reserves. For ten points, name this country formerly led by Hugo Cha \u0301vez and a corrupt government in Caracas.", "answer": "Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela (accept Repu \u0301blica Bolivariana de Venezuela)", "subcategory": "Current Events Other", "category": "Current Events"}, {"question": "This island's native Taino people fought the settlers of La Navidad, which was founded after Columbus' Santa Maria ran aground on this island's western shore. In 2010, this island was rocked by a massive earthquake near the city of (*) Port-au-Prince. For ten points, name this Caribbean island that is politically divided between Haiti and the Dominican Republic and whose name illustrates its possession by Spain.", "answer": "Hispaniola", "subcategory": "Geography World", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "These values exist at a function's critical points when the function is concave down. The graph of y equals x squared has no global one of these points, but y equals negative x squared has one at the origin. A function has one of these points where it stops (*) increasing and begins decreasing. For ten points, name these points, the highest point a graph reaches, contrasted with a function's minimum.", "answer": "maximum (accept supremum)", "subcategory": "Science Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In The Three Musketeers, studs containing these objects belonging to Anne of Austria are given to the Duke of Buckingham and stolen by Milady de Winter. Mathilda Loisel goes into debt to replace paste replicas of these (*) gemstones, one of which is \"As Big as the Ritz\" in an F. Scott Fitzgerald short story. For ten points, name this precious stone set into jewelry in Guy de Maupassant's \"The Necklace.\"", "answer": "diamonds", "subcategory": "Literature Other", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Outmoded types of these religious actions are acedia and vainglory. Believers may compensate for these actions by acquiring a plenary or partial indulgence instead of serving temporal (*) punishment on Earth or in Heaven. Gluttony and wrath are two of the Seven Deadly types of these actions. For ten points, name these actions that go against the commands of God.", "answer": "sins (accept reasonable equivalents like trespasses)", "subcategory": "Religion Christianity", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "A group of people was subjected to this event due to the Treaty of New Echota. Present-day Oklahoma, then a territory, was the destination for many victims of this event, which got its name from the oppression of the Cherokee nation during it. (*) Andrew Jackson supported, for ten points, what nineteenth century event in which tribes of Native Americans were forcibly relocated west of the Mississippi River?", "answer": "Trail of Tears (prompt on descriptions, such as \"removal of Native Americans,\" before \"relocated\" is read)", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A character in this play describes himself as \"constant as the North star\" after being asked to repeal Cimber's banishment. A funeral speech in this play begins, (*) \"friends, Romans, countrymen, lend me your ears,\" and mocks the title statesman's killer, Brutus. For ten points, identify this Shakespeare tragedy about the death of a Roman emperor.", "answer": "The Tragedy of Julius Caesar", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "These objects can be formed when the Tolman-Oppenheimer-Volkovv limit is exceeded, which can cause a gravitational collapse withing the Schwarzchild radius. Spaghettification can result from these objects' extreme (*) gravitational pull, which prevent light from escaping from them. For ten points, name these extremely dark objects in space.", "answer": "black holes", "subcategory": "Science Other", "category": "Science"}], "bonuses": []}